Guide to the Graham H. Stuart Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Graham H. Stuart papers
1926-1955
SC0024
Stuart, Graham Henry, 1886-1983.
2 Linear feet
Manuscripts and printed items pertaining to Stuart's activities in the foreign service, to Latin American affairs and to the Foreign Service Institute.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Graham Stuart, 1965.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Graham H. Stuart was born in Cleveland, Ohio on January 27, 1887. He graduated from Western Reserve University in Cleveland in 1908. He received his N.A. from the University of Wisconsin in 1918 and his Ph.D. there in 1919. Stuart came to Stanford in 1924 as a professor of pol itical science. In 1952 he joined the staff of the Johns Hopkins University School of Advanced International Studies.
Stuart also taught at the summer sessions of such Universities as Duke, the Graduate Institute of International Studies in Geneva, the University of Chicago, Hague Academy of International Law, and served as visiting Carnegie professor of international relations at Toulouse, Poitiers and Montpelier.
In 1942 - 1943 he was an analyst and consultant to the Board of Economic Warfare; from 1943-1945 he served as consultant to the Department of State; and in 1946 he became advisor and Arnerican minister to Tangier and Morocco.
He has been as sociated with the Pan American Scientific Congress; the Harris Institute of Politics; the Institute of World Affairs; the Hoover War Library; the American Political Science Association; the American Society of International Law; Alpha Tau Omega; Phi Beta Kappa; Phi Kappa Phi; Pi Sibma Alpha; and was also a leader of the Round Table.
His publications include: French Foreign Policy, 1921; Latin America and the United States, 1943; Governmental System of Peru, 1925; Tacna-Arica Dispute, 1927; the International City of Tangier; 1931; Conception Americaine des Relations Internationales, 1935; and American Diplomatic and Consular Practice, 1936. Graham H. Stuart is also a regular contributor to American Year Book and an editor of Stanford Books in World Politics.
Description of the Collection
Manuscripts and printed items pertaining to Stuart's activities in the foreign service, to Latin American affairs and to the Foreign Service Institute.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Department of Political Science. Faculty.; Stuart, Graham Henry, 1886-1983.; United States--Diplomatic and consular service.
Collection Contents
- Foreign Service
  - Administration
    - Department of State departmental announcements - 21 announcements re rules, regulations and organization (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Department of State, Foreign Policy in the fields of transportation and communications - proposed plan of organization (carbon typescript)., 1 Oct. 1948. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Department of State request for authorization of official Domestic travel, 23 Nov. 1948. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 2 mimeo. statements for the press re U.S. Govt. fellowships and the David A. Salmon retirement. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Pamphlet on the Foreign Service Act of 1946: to improve, strengthen and expland the Foreign Service of the U.S. and to consolidate and revise the law relating to its administration. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Public Opinion and Parliamentary Diplomacy - copy of the Byron Taylor lecture by Dean Rusk., 27 April 1950. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - TLS to Stuart from II Andy," 4 March 1948 re the School of Advanced International Studies (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - List of students from Turner's Diplomatic School who would be admitted to the Foreign Service Oral Exam. Six Stanford names on list., 29 Nov. 1941. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Foreign Service list, 2 pamplets, April and July 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Confidential report: Some Preliminary Observations and Recommendations on Foreign Service training. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Our Foreign Policy - The Future of the Foreign Serive, a pamphlet., 29 Dec. 1945. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dept. of State and the U.N. - carbon typescript by Lincoln Palmer Bloomfield. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Diplomatists - Career and otherwise. Carbon typescript. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dept. of State publications for the press. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Reorganization of the Dept. of State. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Proposed regulations governing telecommunications of the State Dept. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Pamphlet on "Know Your State Dept. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Diplomacy of a Two-Ocean Navy - carbon typescript by Theodore Roosevelt. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letter to the memebers of the American Foreign Service from the Executive Committee of the American Foreign Service. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - A program leading to the Foreign Service - mimeo. copy (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Press release, 23 April 1946. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Consular Work
    - 6 newspaper articles (a series) entitles "The American Consul in Action and What it Means to be one." From the Christian Science Monitor., 21-26 Oct. 1929. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - newpaper aticles (mounted) taken from the Christian Science Monitor re the life and work of Foreign Service Officers. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 5 radio scripts "Tales of Foreign Service": Islands of Home; Govt. in Limbo; Clerks; Good Neighbor to the North; and Elihu Root, Sec. of State. All written by William C. Hodapp (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Radio script for "Yankee Consol": Mission to Korea - 1883., Written 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pamphlet of rules and regulations for Foreign Service Officials; also an instruction sheet. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General
    - Memorandum on the Act of 14. Feb. 1903, 29 Oct. 1935. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report of the Committee of Publications of the Dept. of State - carbon typescript. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report on the Foreign Service of the U.S. by G. Howland Shaw. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report of the Forign Service Buildings Commission., Jan. 1929. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report on Educational Preparation for the Foreign Service. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Pamphlet on the "Pattern of the Unneutral Diplomat: Robert Lansing and the World War." (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report on Bankrupting our Foreign Service - carbon typescript. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The American Foreign Service in War and Peace - carbon typescript. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report on the Foreign Service: What it is and how to prepare for it. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report on Women in Diplomacy. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report on Foreign Service of the Dept. of Agriculture. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report on a Proposed Course in State Dept. Administration. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report on Langauge and Area Specialization. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report on Dean Acheson Evaluated. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Ramphlet on Diplomats in Modern French Literatire by William Leonard Schwartz, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper clipping of the Amending Act for the grading and classification of clerks in the Foreign Service. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Pamphlet "Treaty Information," Bulletin No. 63, Dec. 1934. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Article from Harper's Magazine "The Dept. of State" by Hubert Herring, Feb. 1937. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Pamphlet "The Foreign Service in Transition" by William P. Maddox, Jan. 1947. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bulletin from the Cumulative Digest of International Law and Relations: New Japanese Embassy Indicates Growing Importance of Post, 10. Nov. 1930. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bulletin from the Cumulative Digest of International Law and Relations: American Foreign Service Building Program, 17 Dec. 1930. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Photostat of Translation of Articles of the Mao-Stalin Secret Pact. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sketch plan of the Battle of Soferino. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Soviet World Policy and the Truman Doctrine - an address delivered at the National Conference of the American Institute of Pacific Relations., 10 April 1947. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report "Democratic State in Relation to International Law and Order, 13 Dec. 1940. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Immigration
    - Booklet on "Right to Protect Citizens in Foreign Countries by Landing Forces, 5 Oct. 1912. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Pamphlet "The Protection of Foreign Lives and Property in Disturbed Areas, July 1929. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Institute
    - Higher Education bulletin on the Foreign Service Institute, 15 Oct. 1947. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1st annual report of the Foreign Service Institute, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - General organization and purposes of the Foreign Service Institute (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Basic officer training of the Foreign Service Institute (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Report on Activities of the Language Training School of the Foreign Service Institute (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Graphs of the training of language offices and basic officer training. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Summary of the School of Advanced Officer Trainings. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Copy of the tentative agenda for a meeting of the Advisory Committee for the Foreign Service Institute, 17 Dec. 1948. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Minutes of the Advisory Committee meetubg, 17 Dec. 1948. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Suggested topics for the Executive Session of the Advisory Committee., 17 Dec. 1948. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Report on Foreign Relations for the Advisory Committee (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 4 TLS to Stuart from William P. Maddoz (Bill) re the Institute: 23 Nov; 26 Nov; 1 Dec; and 6 Dec., 23 Nov; 26 Nov; 1 Dec; and 6 Dec. 1948. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Foreign Service Institute syllabus of the Intermediate Course on Foreign Affairs for the School of Advanced and Specialized Studies on the Institute. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Nationality
    - 5 reports from the Cumulative Digest of International Law and Relations re nationality and naturalization, 8 Oct, 1930; 4 April 1932; 3 Oct. 1934; 19 Dec. 1934; and 2 Dec. 1935. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Article from Harper's Magazine "I Married an American" by Katherine Sweetland. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Passports
    - 3 of Stuart's passports (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Pamplet on "Passport Regulations," revised, 31 March 1938. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Passport and Visa Information" for clerks of courts who take passport applications, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Pamphlet "Notice of Bearers of Passports. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Pamphlet "Passports and Visas. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Report on "The Passport. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Statement of passports issued to govt. employees. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Inofrmation for American citizens traveling to nearby countries. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Passport Division - editorial, historical and regulations sections. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 2 TLS to Stuart from Ruth Shipley, Chief of Passport Division, 25 Nov. 1944; 20 Feb. 1945. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 2 carbons of TL to Mrs. Shipley from Stuart, 27 Oct. 1944; 7 Dec. 1944. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Personal and Miscellaneous
    - Revue des Sciences Politiques" - a pamphlet by Stuart. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 10 notebooks of Stuart's while he was at the Ecole de Science Politique. All holograph in French - contain lecture notes. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Pamphlet of addresses given at a dinner in honor of American professors visiting Geneva. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Passenger lists for: "president Harding," 28 July 1926; "S.S. Santa Lucia," 28 Feb. 1941; and "S.S. Brazil," 23 April 1941. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 2 book reviews by Stuart, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Final programme of the Carnegie Endowment for Interational Peace, Aug 1926. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Program of the 18th season of the Institute of World Affairs, Dec. 1940. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Pamphlet "The Amazons in Elizabethan Literature, July 1940. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Pamphlet "The World Adrift" - A World Affairs Pamphlet, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Official program of the Eight American Scientific Congress, May 1940. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Newspaper clipping with picture re Stuart and his arrical at the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace. From the Standard., 30 March -- (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Itinerary from the American Express Travel service, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Recipe for Brunswick Stew - carbon typescript. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Poster re Stuart speaking for the Tus. Evening Series on "The Good Neighbor Policy." (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Latin American Affairs--Hispanic-American Institute
  - General
    - Report on "The U.S. and Latin America - Argentina in Opposition. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Report on "The Inter-American Highway and the Army Engineers' Pioneer Road, 8 Sept. 1945. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Report on "Inter-American Cooperation." (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Memo on Bibliography on Mexican Oil Expropriation, 5 Nov. 1940. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Copy of a radio discussion by Stuart over shortwave to Latin America. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Press release from the Dept. of State: Copy of the address by the American Delegate to the Chaco Peace Conference (also the Ambassador Designate to the Republic of Colombia)., 4 Jan. 1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Translation of a report on a meeting between the President of the [Colombia] Republic and the American tourists from the Carnegie Foundation. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - U.S. Economic Relations with Latin America (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Pamphlet on "The Program of the Dept. of State in Cultural Relations. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - List of American Hemisphere Division Syudies, classified by country. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Daily Information Bulletin from the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Excerpt from the Atlantic Monthly article "A New Basis for Pan-American Trade." (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Pamphlet "Can the Americas Live Alone?, Feb 1941. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Pamphlet "Rubber on the Rebound - East to West. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Graph of the Americas - how they compare. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Report and chart from the U.S. Dept. of Commerce, 22 Oct. 1942. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - U.S. Economic Relations with Latin America
  - Chile and Equador
    - Charts on Chile's economy. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Report on Trade Development and Economic Warfare Policies toward Equador. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Bulletin from the International Reference Service. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Report to the Sec. of State re Chile during War Time conditions, 23 July 1942. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Penciled notes re Chile. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Directive #5 - A Program for Chile. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Report on Economic Conditions in Chile, Nov. 1942. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Memo to Stuart from P.T. Ellsworth, Chief of the U.N. Division, 13 Nov. 1942. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Report on Chilean Food Situation. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Memo re a meeting with Chilean representatives, 9 Nov. 1942. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Clipping re the Chilean budget, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Report on Chilean power plants and their vulnerability. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 2 surveys of present conditions in Chile with emphasis upon her relations with the U.S. 21 Oct. 1942 and 3 Dec. 1942. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Report "State of the Nation to Congress, 22 July 1947. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Report on Chile - very general. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Chile - a list of holidays and the movie industry. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 5 charts of Chilean economic statistics: Trade with Principal Countries, 1938-1941; Principal Imports for Consumption from Chle. 1938-1940; Principal Exports to Chile, 1938-1941 (2 pages); Principal Imports, 1938-1941 (2 pages); and Princial Exports, 1938-1941. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Peru
    - Memorandum of conversation between Stuart, Normal Armour and Carl Spaeth re Survey of River Plate Affairs, 11 Sept. 1944. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Notes on a memo loaned by Mr. Micou. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Memo from the Board of Economic Warfare. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Report on "Construction of Steel Mills at Chimbote, Peru, 15 Oct. 1942. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Report "Program for Peru (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Report "Peruvian Food Situation (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Bulletins from the Peruvian-American Digest, Aug-Nov 1942. (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Political Science Papers
  - Reports (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Allied Kommandatura: Berlin, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - American Trusteeship in the Pacific, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Importance of Public Opinion in Foreign Policy (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - International Control of Atomic Energy and the Regulation of Armaments. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Interational Regulation of Air Transport., 1948 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Internationalization of Maritime Signaling, Navigational Aids and Rules of the Road, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Kuramoto Incident. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - New Foreign Policy for the U.S. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - New Palestine (3 pages in outline form). (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Postal Diplomacy, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation between the U.S.A. and the Italian Republic (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Trieste (International Law). (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Major Publications
  - The International City of Tangier - manuscript published under the Stanford Bools in World Politics Series by the Stanford University Press, 1955
    - Pages 1-100 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Pages 101-200 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Pages 201-419. Also, extra draft from the manuscript [chapter 3 or 4] "Morocco and the U.S. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - American Diplomatic and Consular Practive - a bound volume, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 22)